Guide to the John William Colenso Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John William Colenso Papers
1855-1908
RG 129
Yale University Divinity School Library
0.5
(1 box)
Writings by and about Colenso document the controversies that surrounded this church leader in South Africa. John William Colenso (1814-1883) was appointed Bishop of Natal, South Africa in 1854. He was a controversial figure due to his stance on polygamy and his theology.
Colenso, John William, 1814-1883
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired in 1970 through Africana Antiquarians (Pty) Ltd. of Port Elizabeth, South Africa.
Biographical / Historical
1814 Jan Born at St. Austell, Cornwall, England
1831-1853 Served as a teacher and tutor, attended St. John's College, Cambridge; served as vicar of Fornett St. Mary in Norfolk.
1846 Jan Married Frances Bunyon who became the mother of his five children: Frances, Harriette, Agnes, Robert, and Francis.
1854 Jan Arrived in Natal to serve as the first bishop of Natal. Shortly after his arrival, controversy was aroused by his stand on polygamy.
1855 Returned to Nantal after a stay of some months in England.
1859-1861 Published a grammar of the Zulu language, a Zulu-English dictionar, manuals of instruction for natives on history, astronomy, geography, etc.
1861 Commentary on St. Paul's Epistle to the Romans published by Colenso was declared full of heresies by Bishop Gray of Capetown.
1862 Colenso published a critical examination of the Pentateuch. His radical theology cause a controversy that shook the Anglican Church in Natal, raising constitutional as well as doctrinal issues. Bishop Gray, as metropolitan of Capetown, claimed to exercise coercive jurisdiction over Bishop Colenso and the power of trying and condemning Colenso.
1863 Dec 16 Bishop Gray pronounced a sentence of deposition followed by excommunication of Colenso. Colenso appealed to the crown and the judicial committee of privy council declared the whole of Gray's proceedings null and void. Colenso returned to his diocese as the legal bishop. Controversy continued to rage as the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel and the Society for the Promotion of Christian Knowledge chose to regard Colenso as canonically deposed.
1864-1875 In general, friendly feelings toward Colenso among the colonists increased until he took an unpopular stand on an issue of native trouble.
1883 Jun Died.
Scope and Contents
This record group contains primarily printed materials by and about John William Colenso, his children, and the Anglican Church in Natal. Colenso was an important figure in South African church history, representative of mid-nineteenth century "liberal" Anglican theology; these writings document his thought and the controversies that he aroused. The material written or published after Colenso's death relates to 1) the continuing constitutional controversy in the Church of Natal or b) his wife and children, particularly his children Harriette and Francis, who continued their father's involvement in native affairs in South Africa.
Arrangement
I. Writings by Colenso, 1855-1879, n.d.
II. Writings about Colenso, 1856-1904, n.d.
III. Writings by Colenso Family, 1907-1908
IV. Photographs and Memorabilia, 1864-1882
Kwazulu-Natal (South Africa) -- Church history; Colenso, John William, 1814-1883; Church of England -- Missions -- South Africa
- Writings by Colenso, 1855-1879, n.d.; Series I
  - "Remarks on the Proper Treatment of Cases of Polygamy, As Found Already Existing in Converts from Heathenism", 1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "A Letter to an American Missionary", 1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "What doth the Lord require of us? Sermon, preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Peter's, Pietermaritzburg", 1879 Mar (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "First Lessons in Science", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "A Sermon Preached in St. Paul's, Durban, on Sunday, Nov. 12th, and in the Cathedral Church of St. Peter's Maritzburg, on Sunday, November 26th" (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Writings About Colenso, 1856-1904, n.d.; Series II
  - "A Review of Dr. Colenso's Remarks on Polygamy" by H. A. Wilder, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Case of the Bishop of Natal" - printed leaflet, 1865 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Bishop of Natal" - two copies of leaflet, in different formats, 1865 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Laymen's Address to the Advocates of the cause of Freedom of Opinion" - printed leaflet, 1865 Jun (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Diocese of Natal, South Africa. Correspondence, Etc.: I. The Sentence of Excommunication by the Bishop of Captown; II. The case of the Rev. A. Tonnesen and the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel", 1866 Mar (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Diocese of Natal, South Africa. Correspondence, Etc.: I. The case of the Rev. A. Tonnesen and the Society for the Propagation of the Gospel; II. The Church of England Defence Association in Natal", 1866 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Colony of Natal, South Africa - Appeal for funds, toward support of any clergy, who in consequence of having paid canonical obedience to the Bishop of Natal, may be unable to obtain the usual salary from the SPG" - printed leaflet, 1866-1877 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Extracts from Natal Witness and the Spectator - printed leaflet, 1866-1867 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Society for the Propagation of the Gospel and the Clergy in Natal: 1. A Sermon by the Rev. J. D. LaTouche, in aid of the Bishop of Natal's Clergy; 2. Extract from the Natal Herald; 3. The Bishop of Natal's Pastoral Address to his Clergy", 1867 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed compilation of letters related to the Church controversy in natal, particularly as regards the disturbance caused by the intrusion of Bishop Twells into the Diocese of Natal, 1867 Jun (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Diocese of Natal, South Africa: I. Letter addressed to the Bishop of Oxford by the Churchwardens...; II. Letter addressed to the Bishop of London by the Rev. Canon Gray..; III. Another letter on the disturbance caused by the intrusion of Bishop Twells...; IV. The Judgment of Judge Phillips on the Churchwardens", 1867 Sep (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Printed compilaton of letters related to the Church controversy in Natal, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Natal Witness on Bishop Colenso", 1883 Aug (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Facsimile of letter to The Rt. Hon. W. E. Gladstone M. P. asking for help for Colenso's widow in the form of a pension from the civil list., 1894 Nov (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "The Southern Cross. May 15, 1894. Church Matters in Natal", 1894 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed letter from the secretary of the Natal Defence Committee, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Church of England in Natal. I. Petition and Memorial to the Archbishop of Canterbury; II. Correspondence between the Archbishop of Canterbury and the Church of England in Natal Defence Committee. An Answer to the Statements of the Archbishop of Capetown.", 1904 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Petition. To the Right Honorable and Most Reverend The Lord Archbishop of Canterbury, Primate of all England." (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Famous Controversies - The Trial of Bishop Colenso", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Writings of Colenso Family, 1907-1908; Series III
  - "Memorandum Communicated by Miss Colenso to her Brother, Mr. F. E. Colenso" by Harriette Colenso, 1907 Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "What a Liberal Government Can Tolerate. Diary of Tilonko's 'Trial' by Court-Martial and fruitless appeals to British Justice. Compiled by his Attorney under Power." by Francis Colenso, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Dinuzulu Special Court" by F. E. C. (Francis), 1908 Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "The Reign of Unlaw in Natal. Miss Colenso's Second Address on Natal Native Legislation", 1908 Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Dinuzulu's Peril" by Francis Colenso, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photographs and Memorabilia, 1864-1882; Series IV
  - Two photographs of Bishop Colenso, 1864, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photograph of St. Mary's church (Grey's Hospital), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Misc. note cards referring to Colenso family, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)